<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Yasoob Khalid</title>
    <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Yasoob Khalid</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 05:00:23 +0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://yasoob.github.io/gci/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up loklak Server on Linux</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/setting%20up%20loklak%20server%20%7C%20linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 05:00:23 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/setting%20up%20loklak%20server%20%7C%20linux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a simple asciinema cast which shows you how you can setup &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/loklak/loklak_server&#34;&gt;loklak server&lt;/a&gt; on Linux (in our case Ubuntu).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://asciinema.org/a/32450.js&#34; id=&#34;asciicast-32450&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Intro to Kivy</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/kivy%20intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 03:34:37 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/kivy%20intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kivy is a fantastic application framework which allows to to make cross-platform GUI applications easily. You can even make Android and IOS applications using kivy. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/#home&#34;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt; of kivy sells it as &amp;ldquo;Open source Python library for rapid development of applications that make use of innovative user interfaces, such as multi-touch apps.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used kivy once before and I really fell in love with it. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/docs/gettingstarted/rules.html&#34;&gt;KV&lt;/a&gt; language gives you immense control over the GUI part of application development. You can use kivy on any OS, let it be Windows, Linux or Mac OSX. The applications created with Kivy can run on Linux, Windows, OS X, Android and iOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know about one more great thing about kivy? It is 100% free to use even in professional business applications. It is distributed under the MIT license which means that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to pay a dime to use it. Some of it&amp;rsquo;s CPU intensive parts are written in C instead of pure Python. This gives you the best of both worlds, the power of C and the ease of use of Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to see the consiseness of Kivy? The following code constitutes a fully working kivy application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from kivy.app import App
from kivy.uix.button import Button

class TestApp(App):
    def build(self):
        return Button(text=&#39;Hello World&#39;)

TestApp().run()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a sample Kivy paint app from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/docs/tutorials/firstwidget.html&#34;&gt;official tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kivy.org/docs/_images/guide-4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kivy Paint app&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future I will love to create a Chemistry application using Kivy. The application would be similar to ChemSketch. I will use Kivy because it provides easy APIs to use Canvas and draw shapes. As that would be the main part of my app, I would love to give kivy a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you liked this short intro to kivy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some useful links for your future endeavours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/#home&#34;&gt;Kivy Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/docs/gettingstarted/intro.html&#34;&gt;Kivy Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kivy.org/docs/tutorials/pong.html&#34;&gt;Pong Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Hugo on Ubuntu 14.04</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/installing%20hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 01:11:10 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/installing%20hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hugo is a static website generator which is written using golang. It is extremely fast and lightweight. You can use it to create a blog or full blown away corporate website. In this post I will show you how you can deploy a blog made with Hugo to GitHub pages. Let&amp;rsquo;s start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.Download the binary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to download the Hugo binary for your platform from GitHub. I will be downloading binaries for 64bit linux as that is what I am using right now. Your system might be 32 bit so kindly keep that in mind. The download link is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases/download/v0.15/hugo_0.15_linux_amd64.tar.gz&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.Extract it in &lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt; folder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to save all of my development related stuff in a separate &lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt; folder in my home. You can easily create this dev folder using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir ~/dev
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and extract the hugo files in this folder. If you are done with this step then move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.Setting up an alias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to setup and alias for hugo. Currently we can call hugo from any folder by running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ~/dev/hugo_0.15_linux_amd64/hugo_0.15_linux_amd64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see the above command is not very user friendly. We are going to change it. Open up your &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file using your editor of choice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ nano ~/.bashrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following text at the end of this file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;alias hugo=&#39;~/dev/hugo_0.15_linux_amd64/hugo_0.15_linux_amd64&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After saving the file type the following command in your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;source ~/.bashrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This updates your terminal session according to your &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file so that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to restart the terminal for the changes to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.Actually creating the new blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now hop over to your Desktop and create a new site/blog using the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd ~/Desktop
$ hugo new site new_site
$ cd new_site
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above command creates a new website in a &lt;code&gt;new_site&lt;/code&gt; folder in your Desktop and &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;s you into that folder. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to create a new page for our website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.Creating &lt;code&gt;about.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the following command in your terminal to create a new &lt;code&gt;about.md&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ hugo new about.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can edit the file using your editor of choice. The above file will be created inside the &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; folder. Just add valid markdown after the &lt;code&gt;+++&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;about.md&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.Create a new post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blog is not complete with a blogpost. You can easily create one by typing the following command in your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo new post/first.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can edit the post in your editor of choice. The post will be created in the &lt;code&gt;content -&amp;gt; post&lt;/code&gt; folder. After you have edited the file, save it and continue with the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.Getting the themes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently we don&amp;rsquo;t have any fancy themes. We can change that by cloning the &lt;code&gt;themes&lt;/code&gt; repo. It can easily be done by keying in the following command in your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git clone --depth 1 --recursive https://github.com/spf13/hugoThemes.git themes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can test various themes by typing the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ hugo server --theme=hyde --buildDrafts
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will generate your blog and you can view it on &lt;code&gt;localhost:1313&lt;/code&gt;. Just change the &amp;ndash;theme flag to test various themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we are ready to actually push our blog to GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.Building the blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all we need to edit the &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;/code&gt; file. Add the following information in it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;baseurl = &amp;quot;http://yasoob.github.io/&amp;quot;
languageCode = &amp;quot;en-us&amp;quot;
title = &amp;quot;Yasoob Khalid&amp;quot;
author = &amp;quot;yasoob&amp;quot;
theme = &amp;quot;hugo-zen&amp;quot;

[params]
  logo      = &amp;quot;/images/logo.jpg&amp;quot;
  copyright = &amp;quot;Yasoob. All rights reserved.&amp;quot;
  twitter   = &amp;quot;https://twitter.com/yasoobkhalid&amp;quot;
  facebook  = &amp;quot;https://www.facebook.com/m.yasoob&amp;quot;
  github    = &amp;quot;https://github.com/yasoob/&amp;quot;
  email     = &amp;quot;yasoob.khld@gmail.com&amp;quot;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace the above variables with your own info. Now type this command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ hugo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will generate your blog inside a &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9.Setup a new repo on GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a git repository in the public folder and commit all the changes. You can easily do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd public
$ git init .
$ git add .
$ git commit -m &amp;quot;created my awesome hugo blog&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now goto GitHub and create a new repo. We will name it &lt;code&gt;yasoob.github.io&lt;/code&gt; for the sake of this tutorial. After that we will add a remote in our repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git remote add origin git@github.com:yasoob/yasoob.github.io.git
$ git push -u origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.Test it out!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can browse to the newly published blog. You can find it at the following url &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;github_username&amp;gt;.github.io/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing Wine 1.8 on Ubuntu 14.04</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/wine1.8%20ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 02:38:37 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/wine1.8%20ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Wine is a Compatibility layer for running windows applications on Linux and Mac OSX. Instead of simulating internal Windows logic like a virtual machine or emulator, Wine translates Windows API calls into POSIX calls on-the-fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I will show you how you can install Wine on Ubuntu 14.04. It is really easy to install it. We will be doing most of our work on the command-line using &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt;. It is the best and easiest way to add &lt;code&gt;ppa&lt;/code&gt;s and install &lt;code&gt;pakages&lt;/code&gt; in linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adding-the-ppa:a312123215a2f39fcfdf0a1148149d1d&#34;&gt;Adding the PPA:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to add the &lt;code&gt;ppa&lt;/code&gt; to your system. You can easily do this by running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo add-apt-repository ppa:ubuntu-wine/ppa
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://imgur.com/tz215JA.png&#34; alt=&#34;adding the ppa&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-the-packages-list:a312123215a2f39fcfdf0a1148149d1d&#34;&gt;Update the packages list:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to update the packages list. We can do that easily as well. Just type in the following command in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://imgur.com/DsOIFXv.png&#34; alt=&#34;updating&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-wine:a312123215a2f39fcfdf0a1148149d1d&#34;&gt;Installing Wine:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we are on the last step. In this step we will install wine itself. Just type the following commands in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install wine1.8
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checkout this Asciinema cast which I recently made to showcase the whole installation procedure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://asciinema.org/a/32603.png&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you go! Wine is installed! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Environment in Python</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/virtualenv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 02:41:53 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/virtualenv/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard of &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;? If you are a beginner,
then you might not have heard about it but if you are a
seasoned programmer then it may well be a vital part of your toolset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;? &lt;code&gt;Virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; is a tool which allows us to
make isolated python environments. Imagine you have an application that
needs version 2 of a library, but another application requires
version 3. How can you use and develop both these applications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you install everything into &lt;code&gt;/usr/lib/python2.7/site-packages&lt;/code&gt; (or
whatever your platform&amp;rsquo;s standard location is), it&amp;rsquo;s easy to end up in a
situation where you unintentionally upgrade a package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another case, imagine that you have an application which is fully
developed and you do not want to make any change to the libraries it is
using but at the same time you start developing another application
which requires the updated versions of those libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will you do? Use &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;! It creates isolated environments
for your python application and allows you to install Python libraries
in that isolated environment instead of installing them globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install it, just type this command in the shell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.. code:: python&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install virtualenv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important commands are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ virtualenv myproject&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ source bin/activate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first one makes an isolated virtualenv environment in the
&lt;code&gt;myproject&lt;/code&gt; folder and the second command activates that isolated
environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While creating the virtualenv you have to make a decision. Do you
want this virtualenv to use packages from your system &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;
or install them in the virtualenv’s site-packages? By default,
virtualenv will not give access to the global &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want your &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; to have access to your systems
&lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;, use the &lt;code&gt;--system-site-packages&lt;/code&gt; switch when creating
your virtualenv like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.. code:: python&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ virtualenv --system-site-packages mycoolproject
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can turn off the &lt;code&gt;env&lt;/code&gt; by typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.. code:: python&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ deactivate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; after deactivating will use your system installation
of Python again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtualenvwrapper:ae2a870b41789da9c4f71e0ac6bfd0c3&#34;&gt;Virtualenvwrapper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtualenv wrapper is a set of extensions for virtualenv. These extensions make your life easier and improve your deveopment workflow. The features of virtualenvwrapper are (taken from project page):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizes all of your virtual environments in one place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrappers for managing your virtual environments (create, delete, copy).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a single command to switch between environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tab completion for commands that take a virtual environment as argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User-configurable hooks for all operations (see Per-User Customization).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plugin system for more creating sharable extensions (see Extending Virtualenvwrapper).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly virtualenvwrapper stores all your virtual environments in one place and allows you to shift from one environment to another quite easily. You can install it by running the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install virtualenvwrapper
$ export WORKON_HOME=~/Envs
$ mkdir -p $WORKON_HOME
$ source /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can create your first environment by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkvirtualenv venv1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that it installed the virtual environment in the &lt;code&gt;~/Envs&lt;/code&gt; directory by running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(venv1)$ ls $WORKON_HOME
venv1 hook.log
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can install the software in the usual way by using pip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(venv1)$ pip install flask
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can create multiple environments and shift from one to another quite easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(venv1)$ mkvirtualenv venv2
(venv2)$ workon venv1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can even copy virtual environments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(venv1)$ cpvirtualenv venv1 dest
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above command creates a new virtual environment with the name of &lt;code&gt;dest&lt;/code&gt;. Lastly you can deactivate a virtual environment by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;deactivate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of other cool virtualenwrapper commands which I did not list here. You can check them out over &lt;a href=&#34;https://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/en/latest/command_ref.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I hope you liked this short intro to virtualenv and virtualenvwrapper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making a Flask app with login functionality</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/flask%20login%20app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2015 04:42:46 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/post/flask%20login%20app/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hi there guys! In this post I will share my experience with you while developing a Flask app with login functionality. The sourcecode of the app is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yasoob/flask-login&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be using the following libraries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flask (obviously)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flask-SQLAlchemy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jinja2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Werkzeug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flask-WTF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First-of-all we will define a &lt;strong&gt;User&lt;/strong&gt; model. It goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class User(db.Model):
    __tablename__ = &#39;user&#39;
    id = db.Column(db.Integer, primary_key=True)
    name = db.Column(db.String(120))
    password = db.Column(db.String(120))
    email = db.Column(db.String(240))

    def __init__(self, name, email, password):
        self.name = name
        self.email = email
        self.set_password(password)

    def set_password(self, password):
        self.password = generate_password_hash(password)

    def check_password(self, password):
        return check_password_hash(self.password, password)

    def __repr__(self):
        return &#39;&amp;lt;User %r&amp;gt;&#39; % self.name
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a couple of things here. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assigned &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; as the tablename&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;created 4 fields with &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt; as the primary_key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;created 2 custom methods, &lt;code&gt;set_password&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;check_password&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modified the output of &lt;code&gt;__repr___&lt;/code&gt; to make it more user-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2 custom methods allow us to save password hashes instead of plain-text passwords. Always make sure that you save only the hashes and not the plain-text passwords so that if you database is somehow compromized, the plain-text passwords are not leaked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;views:6d79db0366d5708a8361ae566681a4cf&#34;&gt;Views:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four views in my app. Namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;login&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;signup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;logout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This route simply redirects to the &lt;code&gt;login&lt;/code&gt; view if the user is not logged in. We check that the user is logged in or not by running the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;if session[&#39;user_name&#39;]:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This only runs if there is a &lt;code&gt;user_name&lt;/code&gt; key in the session dict. So if there is not &lt;code&gt;user_name&lt;/code&gt; in the session dict we simply redirect the user to login by running this code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;return redirect(url_for(&#39;login&#39;),401)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;401&lt;/strong&gt; stands for un-authorized. This status code tells the user that he is not authorized to view this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;login&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this view we create an instance of the &lt;code&gt;LoginForm&lt;/code&gt; and present it to the user if he is not logged in. If the user submits the form correctly and a user with the email specified exists in our server, we redirect the user to the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; view. We check that the user_email is in the database and the password is correct by running the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;user = User.query.filter_by(email=form.email.data).first()
if user is not None and user.check_password(form.password.data):
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is correct then we modify the session variables by running this code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;session[&#39;user_email&#39;] = form.email.data
session[&#39;user_name&#39;] = user.name
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is incorrect then we present the errors to the user and ask him/her to try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;signup&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view is kind-of similar to the login view. In this view we create an instance of the &lt;code&gt;SignupForm&lt;/code&gt; form and present it to the user. If the form is validated on submit then we create a user in our database with the supplied information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we redirect the user to the home view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;logout&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view simply pops the &lt;code&gt;user_name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;user_email&lt;/code&gt; values from the &lt;code&gt;session&lt;/code&gt; dict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one other decorated method as well. It is &lt;code&gt;check_user_status&lt;/code&gt;. It is called before every request. It allows us to modify a couple of variables to our liking. We use it to modify the &lt;code&gt;session&lt;/code&gt; variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:6d79db0366d5708a8361ae566681a4cf&#34;&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here is the &lt;code&gt;session&lt;/code&gt; dict. We use it to check whether the user is logged-in or not. I hope you enjoyed this short intro. You can always checkout the whole source-code of the &lt;code&gt;app.py&lt;/code&gt; file from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yasoob/flask-login/blob/master/app.py&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; to get a better understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 01:00:52 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://yasoob.github.io/gci/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;a href=&#34;http://yasoob.me&#34;&gt;Muhammad Yasoob Ullah Khalid&lt;/a&gt;. I am an &lt;a href=&#34;http://book.pythontips.com&#34;&gt;author&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://pythontips.com&#34;&gt;blogger&lt;/a&gt;, international speaker and &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/yasoob&#34;&gt;Open Source fanatic&lt;/a&gt;. I made this website to document my progress in &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/open-source/gci/?hl=en&#34;&gt;Google Code-in&lt;/a&gt;. I am working with &lt;a href=&#34;http://fossasia.org&#34;&gt;fossasia&lt;/a&gt; which comprises of a group of really awesome people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a partial list of the projects which I have currently completed during this GCI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yasoob.me/learn-git&#34;&gt;Learn Git&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://flasklogin.herokuapp.com/&#34;&gt;Flask login app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yasoob.me/geo_cord&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Your Geolocation?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yasoob/go-reddit&#34;&gt;Go-Reddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also contributed a lot of code and tests to the following repositories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/loklak/python-loklak-api/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=is%3Apr+author%3Ayasoob+&#34;&gt;python-loklak-api&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/loklak/loklak_server/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=is%3Apr+author%3Ayasoob+&#34;&gt;loklak_server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fossasia/gci15.fossasia.org/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=is%3Apr+author%3Ayasoob+&#34;&gt;GCI Fossasia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fossasia/open-event-orga-server&#34;&gt;Open Event Orga Server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>